IL Cafe we have you
covered the end of September sees us
observe World Heart Day it's a good time
to focus on your health on the lifestyle
choices that you're making and indeed on
some of the other aspects of
cardiovascular Wellness welcome to I
Cafe my name is shal and today we've
decided to catch up with two experts to
help us understand a very important
topic and that topic is CPR
now you must be wondering what is CPR
right well you've seen it and um I have
to say unfortunately in this country a
lot of us have only been exposed to CPR
on screen on Cinema or some you know
television serial that sort of a thing
where we've seen a person deliver
cardiopulmonary resuscitation to a
patient in need or someone in need uh
but the thing is what is fortunate is
that there is information available on
what CPR is it's only about connecting
the right experts with the right
information to the Right audience so
we're going to talk a little bit about
CPR today on our uh World Heart Day
related podcast it comes ahead of the
day itself and who are the who are the
guests who going to be joining me over
here well our guest speaker today is
none other than Dr rmit vilu he's an
anesthesiologist with a diploma in
critical care uh more than 10 years of
experience in ICU um as a as a specialty
and critical care and he heads in fact
critical care for suran SAA Hospital in
chimur in Bombay so that's a little bit
about Dr vilu and there's also our guest
from The icso Lombard World who's
joining us Dr Sharma I should say Dr
Akash Sharma he's a as you guessed it a
doctor himself by education he's also an
ex entrepreneur and someone who has a
deep interest in experience in
healthcare Tech so that is going to be a
big part of our chat on U on the show
today he currently leads outpatient
Health Products wellness and the IL take
care application strategy for the
organization thank you so much to the
two of you for joining us on I Cafe
today welcome to the show how are you
good thank you good to know that the
people in charge of other people's uh
Health are good you know it's always a
good thing to hear that but my first
question for you is uh you know is for
you Dr WIIL we we've heard so much about
CPR right that phrase or the
abbreviation is now not a you know
uncommon one for all of us why is it
important for us on this special podcast
to be aware of what CPR is all about
well that's an absolutely to question
you know first thing CPR or
cardiopulmonary resuscitation you know
it's a life- saving technique you know
uh it can be used when somebody's
breathing or heartbeat stops suddenly so
it's a combination of chest compressions
and rescue breaths which can be given at
a specific time and you know it can
restore the vital organs with the blood
circulation and it can increase the
chances of somebody surviving a cardiac
arest so CPR basically educating people
about it it generates awareness and
people can be first responders in such
kind of situation so this Bridges the
Gap you know till you know the pros
arrive at the scene basically cardiac
arisk can happen anywhere at any time to
anybody so you know nobody is out of
risk in today's world so basically
learning is very easy and accessible to
all you know being ready to use CPR can
make a massive difference in the crisis
situation and mainly you know in you
know it makes Common People a hero at
that moment so yes it is very important
to save somebody's life by giving CPR
Whenever there is a event or whenever
there is a card AR you know when you say
anyone can actually learn uh CPR do you
really mean that or do I have to have
some sort of a like medical background
to be able to administer CPR to someone
in need so CPR has two components it has
a basic life support and the advanced
cardiac life support so when you talk
about a basic life support anyone anyone
with no medical background at all can
learn it at any point of time it's just
a single day score a few hours into it
and you are an expert no I absolutely
agree with Dr V on this and I believe
the golden R is what we refer to and I
believe in a country like in India where
health or the health assistance doesn't
or emergency health support doesn't come
immediately uh accessibility is a
challenge uh more so in a tier two and
three cities it's good to have somebody
around us who can administer this or
save life or our self being
knowledgeable uh to do this to the
people I believe through this R some
people get that benefit look forward to
that right I'm going to come back to you
Dr vilu uh tell us what are the various
steps involved in CPR to somebody what's
uh what do you do when you find yourself
in a situation like
this no no absolutely you know CPR is
just a series of steps so make sure that
the person who in Cardiac Arrest is
lying flat on a heart surface you know
so place the peel of your palms on the
lower middle part of the chest bone you
know and start with your interlock
fingers so you know then you can start
compressing the chest the compression
should be at least 2 in deep and 100 to
120 in a minute and we just have to make
it sure that after every 30 compressions
we have to give a rescue breath two
rescue breaths and when we are giving
the rescue breath we should be sure that
there is a chest rise so that we know
that the breath is going inside now we
have to just repeat it till the
paramedics or the help
arrives Dr Sharma anything that you
would like to add what Dr B said this is
more referred to as three C's or five
C's of CPR itself right so that means
check for breath and Consciousness and
then uh seek help uh or check for help
third one is cover the nose and the nose
and then the third one last one will be
the PO compressions right so that
normally is how the CPR normally in
simple sense to understand what are the
few steps and how you need to go about
it is kind of taught or educated yeah
yeah so there you go our experts have
given us an understanding of the steps
involved in administering uh CPR or
cardiopulmonary resuscitation to someone
in need uh hopefully that never that
moment never comes in your life and
everybody is safe and healthy again
wishes on the occasion of World Heart
Day that comes up later in September but
to move into the next question right uh
Dr Vu we still notice a lot of people
who are a little bit apprehensive when
it comes to you know getting into the uh
groove of action
doing the right thing and saying okay I
know CPR and I can maybe you know help
in some way they hold back a little bit
why do you think this is the case uh
with some of us well that's an excellent
question you know uh there are several
reasons first of all I would like to say
that it's a fear of making mistake or
causing any harm it's like when you're
giving CPR or chest compressions there
is always a possibility of breaking a
rib but you know breaking a is still
better than not doing it at all you know
and secondly you know maybe many aren't
aware that how crucial CPR is and how
easy it is to learn so thirdly some
people you know hesitate to step in
during emergencies you know often due to
feeling powerless or anxious so these
things are abolished when you learn CPR
you know once you know it you can jump
into the situation and be the hero that
the person needs and where does one
learn you know I forgot to ask you this
I asked you for steps very smartly I did
that but then I forgot to ask where does
one learn this right but how does one
learn to be a first responder are there
courses that that are available in this
particular
there are there are coures courses
around like I said BLS basic life
support so there are few institutes
which teaches such courses and it's a
single day course so you can just uh
check it online and find the nearest one
to yourself and get enrolled yeah please
make a note all of our viewers on this
particular podcast you know if there's a
skill that you really want to pick up in
the year 2023 and there aren't too many
months really left of it soon we're
going to be making resolutions for the
next year but we not there yet we still
have a few months and like uh Dr Vu said
it it just takes about a day of training
and then you can go back for a refresher
course as is required uh let me come to
the next question that I have for you
with respect to anxiety you addressed it
right um how do motivate people to learn
CPR and also overcome these hesitations
so education and awareness are the key
you know we need to spread the word
about the importance of CPR and how
straightforward it is to pick it up know
offering CPR trainings in schools
workplaces communities it can make a
huge difference around plus legal
protections like a Good Samaritan act
you know whenever person you know helps
somebody who's in card should not worry
about the legal implications of it so if
people are protected in that sense I
think they will you know jump into the
situation and try to help somebody
absolutely and be the hero of the day Dr
Sharma what about yeah so I would say
that uh the main aspect is awareness and
education and I feel that we don't
emphasize that enough from our probably
this should be something that should be
taught at school level or High School
level at least uh it's a good skill it's
uh something that's very useful because
event can happen uh with anyone with any
age group right it's important to
understand how to do it it's important
when to do it and also more important to
understand how to do it correctly so all
this can be covered at the in a right
setting and I think we should start at
the school level at least for college
level to build more Consciousness around
the cprn value absolutely I can't agree
with you more right in fact uh when you
look at the broader Financial awareness
space as well uh a lot of experts that
I've spoken to on typical Money Matters
related things also say you know why
don't we start this sort of thing early
in life and same thing with life-saving
skills indeed you know as you've rightly
pointed out needs to be part of the
curriculum uh and it's not that
difficult I would imagine to implement
one of these as a subject schools and
colleges but let's come to something
else that you seem to be very very
passionate about technology and
Healthcare coming together in one person
and that person is Dr Sharma so tell us
about you know uh we have something very
cool over here at ICS lumbar the I take
care app can you tell us about this
One-Stop wellness and insurance solution
if I may call it that so uh the I'll
take your application it comes from the
S of ICS lard and we are the number one
private insurance company of India we
have build this platform with an that it
should give users uh enabling tool in
which they can assess their health and
considering cardiac health is one of the
key area and one of the major risk for
us as a nation right where the lifestyle
decision are the highest this face scan
tool basically is a very good uh role in
that so the feature of the face scan is
such that if you have the application
you can just scan yourself for 30
seconds scan your face and it give you
some primary risk indicators about your
cardiac health one would be your blood
pressure it would give you something
about your oxygen saturation but also
gives you something about your cardiac
variance right right it's an indicator
as Dr B would also tell you that it is
an indicator that helps you understand
that how receptive or how sensitive is
your cardiac function Vis the stress
that you have now the stress could be an
active stress or a passive stress and it
can lead to all sorts of EV and
unfortunately but in many case it can
can make an individual recipient or
likely recipient of CPR itself the
subject that we have here so we feel
that this something that we bought out
it's a it's a cdso certified feature it
is and something that uh people should
have in their pocket and should use it
often I completely agree with you and
this is the day and age of uh technology
coming or you know inserting value into
our lives and spaces that we didn't
believe could be revolutionized by
technology at all and Dr Vu I'm sure
you've seen this right amongst your
patients who are bipping out of course
there's always Google Dr Google is
always consulted before for Dr wilu that
must be a thing that really annoys you
but uh we have to live with this sort of
reality but I'm sure you know you're
also uh sort of gladdened by the way
people are adopting technology to stay
fit whether it's a Fitbit that you're
wearing or any wearable device uh CGM
you know now nowadays I see a lot of
people who don't have diabetes and yet
want to figure out what their blood
sugar picture is all about so they
implant themselves with one of those you
know devices uh tell us what you think
of this coming together of something
like you know like an I take care an
appp uh with uh Technologies like face
scan built into it and you know people
being able to focus on their own health
well certainly the face scan feature is
a stand out aspect of the IL take care
app you know it lets the user check
their key Health vitals in a single face
scan like Dr Sharma also said you know
30 seconds and you get all your vitals
in your hand so it's a quick and easy
way to monitor your health on the go so
I guess in today's technological
advancement of Health should also be one
of the priorities and you know this
health field should also advance in the
similar way so this does help everybody
around to get healthy and with the
monitoring that they need I would say
absolutely I can't agree more with you
you know uh things like face scan are
truly of value instead of watching
Netflix watch the face scan that is
available on the on the I take care and
know no comment because I'm constantly
watching Netflix myself so please go
ahead and enjoy but you know exactly
what I mean uh Dr Sharma to come back to
you right uh some of the other benefits
and features if you can highlight about
the I take care app that would be great
for our viewers so apart from the
cardiac function monitoring that face
scan offers we also have certain other
feature that help in self assessment for
example we have a HRA which helps users
and it's a very effective way of user to
engage with the application and tell
about what the things they're doing
right and wrong and get a score out of
it and also apart from that there is a
doctor assistance that is their
nutritionist so it's basically whole
ecosystem centered around people living
a healthier life with all the coaches
experts and assessment tools that can be
enabled through a digital feature while
such as tracking your steps if you want
to uh track it through the application
also uh mental coach and counselors we
have on the application so have whole
host of that thing created and curated
for our some of our policy holders and
uh even if you're not a policy holder
you can still go on an application and
uh use a t do feature speak to our
doctors and seek a consultation so
that's something we kept open and even
the F scan is open for everyone so I
mean the application is there for people
to access and use and will'll be happy
if people take benefit of that and
something comes to mind on an earlier is
Cafe episode I remember one of our
leaders uh in the organization has
spoken of how this is more about the
health of the individual this is not
really about the insurance aspect the
product aspect of it really you know
comes much later so I love the way uh
the focus is really on the individual
and them taking their own health and
lifestyle into their hands and then
thinking about insurance is just one of
the things that happens in the course of
uh that mindset that we trying to
develop like focus on yourself
absolutely right absolutely so the
intention about I'll take care is that
moving uh just with a our relationship
with a policy holder moving not just as
a facilitator of uh risk coverage but
moving as a custodian of care for them
and I take care basically becomes that
Hub that offers all those enablement and
engages us with our policy holder in
that L I'm going to wrap up we've spoken
quite a bit about the I take care app
we've spoken about face scan we've had
Dr wiu's views on Tech and Healthcare as
well uh with one last message from uh
the both of you since you're experts and
Dr Vu you're indeed someone from
critical care as a as an area of
specialization is there a message that
you'd like to leave all of our uh
viewers on the occasion of World Heart
Day we do know that cardiovascular
illnesses are you know one of the number
one killers in this country along with
diabetes
um a word of caution something on CPR
would be good to get some words of
wisdom to wrap up from
you well at the end I would just like to
say you know okay in today's world uh
you have to take care of your heart you
cannot take it for granted and age is
not a factor as of now you know I've
seen people with the age of 20 also
dropping dead so one should you know
learn and know CPR so that they can
offer it you can offer it to somebody
you don't know but you know if there is
a condition or situation in your own
family and you're unable to help it out
you know that guil stays for a very long
time so take care of yourself give your
health a priority use the health apps
you know I'll take your app there to
help you out with things and you know
learn CPR with either a professional
training or at least take a course or
see how it's done on the internet if you
don't have time to go anywhere but you
know learn this important tool and let
it be there with you at every point of
time anything Dr sh you would like to
add so thank you so I think I'll second
what you just said and I believe that
cpra the what we're focusing on right
now more and more people should make
themselves familiar with it uh
understand that the help is at that
particular time the help is only going
to be coming from the person next to you
and that person at that time if you did
fail to take initiative to make them
aware or educate yourself for it then at
the end of the day you should share the
partly of a blame if uh you miss out on
that
go right so it's important for all of us
to definitely be aware about CPR yeah
and thank you to the two of you for
joining us on the special podcast on the
special episode in fact around World
Heart Day and I want to say something to
you which on behalf of all of our
viewers I would imagine you know most
people in the healthare space never get
told they get asked for advice you know
first person to call if you have a
doctor in the family Dr Vu and Dr Sharma
must be very aware on speed dial you
know I have a call today can you tell me
what I should be taking no matter what
your specializations I've seen that
happen to doctors and the family but
please do take care of your health as
well and thank you so much for the great
work that both of you do do in your
respective fields for the health and
well-being of each one of us thank you
for joining us today thank you thank you
for having us yeah thank you